SWARAT CHAUDHURI:
In this course.
You have seen a lot of
different kinds of uses of LLMs.
And today, I'm going to
emphasize the use of LLMs
as a tool of scientific
and mathematical discovery.
And in particular,
there's going to be
an emphasis on the
ability of LLMs
to discover abstract concepts
and how this can accelerate
these discovery processes.
OK, so let us dive in.
Let us start with the problem
of mathematical discovery.
This is, of course, one
of the grandest challenges
known to humanity.
Now, how does the process
of mathematical discovery
look like?
There is the-- first,
the process of modeling
where you are, getting
inspired by some sort
of a real-world
phenomenon, and then
modeling it in terms of
a variety of definitions
and concepts.
Now, once you have a set of
definitions, at that point,
you may want to conjecture
various properties
of these definitions.
And then these are potentially
candidate theorems and lemmas.
And then there is this
process of rigorous reasoning
where you are actually
proving these statements.
And this process is, for
human mathematicians,
intrinsically social.
You are convincing each
other about the rigor
of your reasoning and the
value of your conjectures.
But this process just
continues in this sort
of an iterative loop.
So you may see proofs
and counterexamples,
and these may influence
your models as well as
your conjectures.
And this process
just goes on, right?
That the history of mathematics.
Now, the dream of the
field of AI for math
is that you want to
automate substantial pieces
of this process,
and as a result,
you want to accelerate
this process even more.
You want to be able to
discover new kinds of math.
And this includes
settling known conjectures
but also potentially coming
up with new conjectures.
And then there is the
setting of natural sciences,
that is also going
to be something
I'll cover in this lecture.
And here, unlike
in math, you are
engaging with the real world.
There is this process
of theory building
where you're coming up with
hypotheses about the universe,
and then you are
using these hypotheses
to design experiments, and
then you are experimentally
validating them, right?
And this experimental validation
process creates new data.
And then this data leads
to new kinds of theories,
for example, by refinement
of the existing hypothesis.
Or in some cases, you
may want to just come up
with entirely new concepts
and new predictions.
So the ambition of the
area of AI for science
is to automate hypothesis
generation and experiment
design.
Now, the key ideas in
the areas of AI for math
and AI for science at this
point are that, number 1, search
is a really powerful concept.
And so, we want to imagine
these spaces of hypothesis,
conjectures, and proofs and
systematically search them.
Now, this is, of course,
a very massive space.
There are all these
potential statements
about various
mathematical objects,
and there are all
these hypotheses that
are possible in the universe.
And this space is
clearly infinite.
Now, how do you explore this
space in a tractable way?
Well, you use prior knowledge to
prioritize directions of search.
And that's also
how humans proceed.
We don't just do
discovery in a vacuum.
We read existing papers, and
sometimes we incrementally
advance on them.
And sometimes we
make a big leap.
But that prior knowledge
is always of value.
But then also we
learn from experience
how and how not to do
this sort of exploration.
You find out that you made
certain choices while building
your theory, and then
you find that this just
didn't work, right?
And that's experience for you.
And then you use this
experience to potentially take
completely new directions.
And then another piece
that is very important--
has been very important to the
history of math and science,
has been to discover
abstract concepts and tools.
So, for example, the
idea of calculus,
that really sped up the
progress of science after it
was invented.
Similarly with
algebra and, really,
all major branches of
mathematics, came from the need
to abstract some sort
of real-world process.
And then, the value
of these abstractions
is that they speed up both
this process of exploration
and also this learning process
that I previously mentioned.
Now, if you think of
it, LLMs bring something
to the table regarding
each of these criteria.
So, for example,
if you are doing
a search in a very large
space of potential scientific
hypotheses, and LLM has
inside it a lot of knowledge
about what sort of
hypotheses have historically
tended to work in science.
And so, this knowledge
can potentially
help you direct
the search process.
And then, also in
this course, you
have seen examples
of LLM agents.
And in this class, you are
going to see more of this.
So these are
systems that contain
inside them LLMs as modules.
But they are also
interacting with the world,
and they are learning
from experience.
And this experience
is gathered as data
and then often stuck
into the prompt.
But sometimes you can even
do reinforcement learning
or other kinds of modification
of the LLM's weights.
But the point is that there
are all these established
methods for doing
learning combined
with the use of language
models, and that
is something that we can
exploit here as well.
Now the use of LLMs
for abstraction,
this is something that's
not well explored yet.
This is a really
new idea, but I'm
going to give you some evidence
as to why there might be
a lot of things going on here.
And there is
certainly a lot more
to be done about the use
of LLMs in constructing
new concepts and new tools.
So I think that LLM agents have
tremendous, endless promise
in mathematical and
scientific discovery.
And the reason is that, so
far as all of these ideas go,
LLMs have a potential to
contribute with regards to each.
So this may all seem
somewhat abstract.
So I'm going to now jump
into some concrete results.
And this lecture is
divided into two pieces.
In the first part, we are
going to talk about AI
for mathematical discovery.
And then in the
second part, we are
going to talk about AI
for scientific discovery.
And in each of these
cases, I'm going
to show you some LLM
agents built using
quite different algorithms.
But we'll see that these agents
realize many of these ideas
that we talked about
in the previous slide.
OK, so let's talk
about AI for math.
Over the last few years,
there's been tremendous interest
in this field.
Here's Terry Tao
from 2023, talking
about how AI from
that year can already
generate suggestive
hints and help
with the mathematical process.
And he predicted
that by 2026, AI
can become a
trustworthy co-author
in math research papers and
in other fields as well.
Now, 2026 is not yet
here, but I would
say that this prediction seems
very plausible as of now.
Now, in terms of
concrete systems,
o1, when it was introduced,
one of the highlights
was that it did really well in
various competition mathematics
problems.
So here is a plot.
It shows how o1 does
compare to GPT-4o.
And as you see, accuracy in
this particular competition,
AIME 2024, has gone
up very substantially.
And then, of course,
last year, my colleagues
at Google DeepMind,
they built this system
that achieved silver medal-level
performance at the IMO.
And you've already heard a
talk about that in this course.
So I'm not going to go
into further detail--
or to much more detail
about that in this talk,
but you know that
it's impressive,
and it uses a lot of very
impressive machinery.
Now, one question that I
think is important to ask
is that is it all going
to be done just with LLMs?
In other words, do you need any
sort of additional machinery
that combines LLMs with,
for example, actions?
This is really
the characteristic
that distinguishes LLM
agents from just basic LLMs.
And so, I would say that there
are certainly still believers
in the potential
of just LLMs alone
to do everything after
being trained on language.
But I am personally a
little bit skeptical
about that possibility.
Now, that said, one must admit
that over the last couple
of years, just LLMs
have come a long way.
So here is the picture of
how you train an LLM on--
for these sorts of
mathematical settings.
So you're going to start
with a pre-trained LLM.
Then you're going to train it on
math-related web docs and then
problems with step-by-step
solutions, problems
with tool-integrated solutions,
and so on and so forth.
And then, ultimately, you
have this LLM that can use,
for example, Python APIs and
that can solve math problems.
And this has, again, as
I said, come a long way.
So, for example, here is a
problem from the Putnam Math
Competition from last year.
And o1's response
on this problem
is actually very reasonable.
And as these systems are
getting better and better,
it seems like they're solving
more and more problems that
are of this nature that are
similarly hard-- or harder.
But that said, there are
some fundamental weaknesses
of this neural-only
approach that you'd
get with just a basic LLM.
And the reason is that--
or one fundamental
reason is that there
is this issue of data scarcity.
In order to do rigorous
mathematical reasoning, not just
computing answers to
well-posed questions,
you need to have a lot
of high-quality traces
of mathematical reasoning.
Or, alternatively, you would
need high-quality reward
functions.
And this is difficult to get
just with human-produced data
beyond high school or
competition settings.
And then a second
reason, fundamentally,
is that natural language
reasoning is hard to verify.
And this is something that
is a fundamental weakness
of these language-only models.
And there are even
settings where
you can apply this sort
of mathematical reasoning
where, for example,
when you are doing
mathematical reasoning
about real-world systems
and the behaviors of these
systems have real consequences,
so edge cases are
really critical.
So in these cases you want
your mathematical reasoning
to be really robust
and rigorous.
And unfortunately,
language-based, purely neural
mathematical reasoning
tends to not be this way.
And so, it is entirely
possible that scaling is going
to solve all of these problems.
But as I said, I'm a little
bit skeptical about this.
So in this talk, I'm
going to demonstrate
an alternative strategy,
which is similar in many ways
to AlphaProof, which
you saw previously,
but which is more of
an LLM agent approach
that is an alternative to this
sort of purely neural, purely
language-driven kind of model.
So this alternative involves
formal representations, just
like in AlphaProof.
So there's an entire
literature that
is building up that follows
this kind of strategy.
And so here, what you do is
that rather than just operating
in this space of
informal problem
statements and informal
solutions, you would be,
first, doing what is
called autoformalization.
So you're going to go from
the informal statement
to a formal statement in a
language, like Lean or Coq,
or Isabelle.
And lean, in particular, is
what is used for AlphaProof.
But there are other
frameworks like this as well
that have a very long history.
Now, the appeal of these
sorts of formal frameworks
is that a proof can be
written in a step-by-step way,
just like code.
And not only that, a
proof can be checked.
You can check if a proof
that you have written
in this formal language actually
implies a certain property
that you started out
with, so this theorem
that you started out with.
And so, the idea is that you
would then, in the second phase,
take this formal
problem statement,
and then you would be feeding
it to a neural prover, which
is going to come up with
this sequence of steps,
which are also called tactics,
these rules that you apply.
So these are tactics, and
you apply them one by one.
And then at the end, you
get to this QED stage,
where you have
nothing left to prove.
And so that's how this
process would work.
And the advantage here is that
if you think of the verification
challenge that I
mentioned earlier,
where you want to check whether
a claimed proof is actually
a proof, this is
something that you
can establish relatively easily
using a proof assistant, right?
And in terms of the data
issues, so the appeal
of this kind of verifiability
is that during training time,
you can synthetically generate
a very, very large number
of candidate proofs.
And then you can immediately
get feedback on whether or not
these proofs are correct.
So this turns this
difficult problem of proof
into this kind of a
game-playing task, which
you can approach with really
a version of reinforcement
learning.
And this is what, for
example, AlphaProof did.
Although I'll show
here that you can also
take a more LLM-based
approach to this problem.
And in fact, you can build up
on these pre-trained language
models and only have a pretty
thin layer on top of that.
And that still does
quite interestingly well.
OK.
So just to go into a
little bit more detail
about these formal
representations,
even though you may have seen
this in the AlphaProof lecture,
I'll just quickly recap--
recapitulate this.
So here is a theorem
that we are--
let's say, we are
trying to prove.
And what this says
is that if x is even,
then x square is even as well.
So the theorem
statement over here
says that x is a natural number.
And then it says that x
being even implies x square
is also even.
So modulo 2, it's--
the remainder is zero.
So now, in order
to prove this, you
are going to apply this
sequence of tactics,
as I said previously.
Now, it's important to note
that the system, that the proof
assistant, it has a
certain state that
depends on what the
original theorem is
and which tactics you
have applied so far.
So, for example,
in the beginning,
you would have a state
that looks like this.
Now, just to spell this
out, what this means,
it says that there is one
goal that you currently
need to prove, and that goal is
that under this context, which
is that x is a natural number,
this is the variable that you're
allowed to use.
And then this symbol,
turnstile, means that this
is what you need to prove.
So this is basically the theorem
that you're starting out with
before you have
applied that tactic.
Now, you have this
state, and then
you apply the tactic, which is,
you can think of it if you're
thinking of this as a
reinforcement learning setup,
you are applying an action.
And so, you apply that action,
and that leads to a new state.
And then this state
here looks like this.
So this intro
tactic, what it does
is that it introduces
this new hypothesis, which
over here now says
that, OK, let us assume
that x is even along with--
sorry.
Yeah x is even along with
x being a natural number.
And this property
that x is even,
we are going to
give it a name, h.
And then under this context,
which is really like,
you have now declared
a new variable
which has a certain
type attached to it.
So now you are trying to show
that this x squared is even
as well.
And then you apply
this next tactic,
which leads to another state.
So these tactics are
written by humans
and they encode various rules of
simplification in mathematics.
And so what you
are really doing is
that for each of these rewrite
rules that you are applying,
the state is changing.
So, for example, now
the state has changed
to you showing that if--
so this x modulo 2 times x
modulo 2, the whole thing modulo
2, that is equal to zero.
And then the next rewrite
is going to simplify this.
And then, finally,
you will end up
with zero equals zero basically.
And at that point,
you're going to hit QED
because your goal will
just disappear, right?
So each of these
rules you can think
of as simplifying the state.
And then at the end, ideally
you want to end up in this state
where there are no open goals.
And at that point,
you can end the proof.
So that's what these formal
proof assistants look like.
Really, they're state machines
where you have the proof state.
And then these actions,
which are these tactics.
And then they lead
to a new proof state.
And your goal really is to
find a sequence of tactics
that take you from this initial
state of the prover to this QED
state, where there are no
more goals to be discharged.
OK, so now let's talk
about the two phases
that I mentioned previously.
The autoformalization phase
is something like this.
You are starting with this
informal math statement.
There exists an infinite
number of primes.
And then there is this
proof of this as well in
natural language.
And now you are applying
your autoformalization model.
And later I'll talk a little bit
about how this could be done.
But the version 0
of this would be
that you throw a language model
at this informal statement,
and then out comes this
formal theorem, right?
And so this one is in Lean.
Now what this says is that--
well, I won't read
this thing in detail,
but maybe I can read
the theorem statement.
It says that, so for
all n there exists
a p such that p is bigger than--
greater than or equal to n,
and then p is also
a prime, right?
So that's how you
establish that there's
an infinite number of primes.
And then the rest
of it is the proof.
So then, let's
assume that you have
done this sort of
formalization, you
have a formal
statement of a theorem,
and now you're
trying to prove it.
So previously, I showed you
that there are these tactics,
these simplification rules
that you could apply.
But now you can imagine a search
problem where at each state
there is a set of potential
tactics that you could apply.
And this leads to the
creation of a search tree.
And then your goal
is to basically find
a path in this tree
that ends up at QED.
Now, of course, the complexity
of here is that at each point
you can have a very, very large
number of potential branches
in this tree.
And then, also, this tree
can be quite deep, right?
Because if you're talking
about really advanced
mathematical theorems,
you could end up
with proofs that are thousands
and thousands of lines long.
And so, this is a
far harder problem
than any game-playing
problem that we
have been able to solve so far.
So it's remarkable to see
the kind of progress that
has already happened in this
task over the last few years.
Now, AlphaProof, of course,
you have already seen.
You've seen this picture.
There's this formalizer network
that does this formalization
into formal problems.
And then the solver
network, it tries
to generate these formal proofs.
One big insight was that
even more formalized problems
are still helpful for learning.
And this sort of proof
the solver network this
is being trained with RL.
And then, one big insight was
that you could complement RL
training with test-time RL when
you're actually doing the IMO
or any other-- solving any other
math problem you could would
generate--
you could basically do this
sort of test-time RL on that.
But again, you have
seen all of this.
So I'll move on.
The approach that I'm
going to talk about today,
this is called COPRA.
This was published in a paper
at the Conference of Language
Models last year.
And this is led
by my PhD student
at UT Austin, Amitayush Thakur.
Now, this is the overall
picture of COPRA.
It still has this view of
interaction between an LLM
that is predicting
the proof steps
and the actual prover
that is executing
the step that is
proposed by the LLM
and then giving you a new state.
However, the difference
is that while AlphaProof
does this sort of advanced
reinforcement learning
for training.
So here, you're just taking
this sort of an LLM agent
approach, where you
have a frontier LLM,
and the frontier LLM is
being provided the proof
state and some information
from the history of the search
so far.
And then it is
making a prediction
as to what's the next
step that you should take.
And then you are taking that
step, and you are executing it,
and then you are getting back
a new state of the proof.
And then this process
is continuing, right?
Now one important
thing is that there
is an external search that is
going on, a depth-first search.
And then inside the depth-first
search, you are doing all this,
right?
But it is fundamentally
different in the sense
that everything is in context.
There is no actual adjustment
to the weights happening.
But what is interesting
is that even
with a relatively small
amount of compute,
this approach was still
able to do quite well.
And so, I think
that this strategy
has a lot of long-term promise.
For one, because it immediately
leverages advances in LLMs,
as, for example, you go
from GPT-4 to o1 to o3
and to maybe someday
GPT-5, then you're
going to immediately leverage
those advantages-- advances.
And it also has this ability
to integrate natural language
and formal language reasoning,
because ultimately, you
are just using an
LLM to generate
the proofs in the formal--
as formal language,
but at the same time,
the LLM has the ability to
do natural language as well.
So this is something
you can benefit from.
And I'm going to show
concrete examples of this
in a little bit.
Another thing is
that it's also--
this strategy is also
applicable even if there is
no corpus of training problems.
Now, one of the challenges
in doing AI for math,
once you go outside of settings
such as math competitions,
is that you're really trying
to solve a new problem, right?
So if you're a math
researcher, you're
trying to solve a new problem
that, by design, is quite
different from the problems
that a lot of other people
have solved previously.
So in such a situation,
it's a bit challenging
to create a corpus
of training problems
and then do training
of an RL agent.
However, with an
in-context learning agent,
the appeal is that
you can still use it.
The LLM has inside it a
ton of prior knowledge,
and that knowledge is something
that you could benefit from,
right?
And the LLM can, for
example, bring in knowledge
about related problems,
even though it's not
been explicitly trained on them
beyond the pre-training stage.
And in the longer run, of
course, the two approaches
of in-context learning
and explicit training,
these are not incompatible.
So you could imagine the
in-context learning agent being
used to generate a lot
of different traces
by interaction with
the proof assistant,
and then you could use
them for doing fine-tuning.
Now, one question that
you may have over here
is that, well, so
do I really need
to even have Lean in that case?
Couldn't I just rely
on the LLM alone?
And I would say that
the difference here
is that this interaction
with the proof assistant
is still providing a very
strong form of grounding.
So, for example, if you take
a step predicted by the LLM
and then you find that this
is actually an invalid step,
you're going to get
that feedback right away
from the proof assistant.
And you can take that feedback,
and you can then stick it back
into the prompt of the LLM.
And then you can
ask it to continue.
And then, hopefully, it
will learn from its mistake
and carry on, right?
So in the long
run, it's possible
that once you have generated a
very, very, very large number
of traces via interaction
with the prover,
maybe you have fine-tuned your
LLM on this-- all this data,
and then the LLM
is progressively
getting better and better.
And there is a point
beyond which it just
doesn't make any mistakes
with this kind of proof.
Maybe we'll get there someday,
but we are still pretty far away
from that possibility.
So at least, as of now, I think
that this sort of interaction
between LLM and proof assistant
is still extremely valuable.
OK, so here is this COPRA system
in a little bit more detail.
So what is going
on here is that you
are starting with
a formal theorem,
but you could also have
some informal hints.
You could imagine bringing
autoformalization into this
picture as well, but we didn't.
And so, the first
step is that you
create a prompt based on the
statement of the theorem.
And then you feed it
to a frontier LLM,
and you just ask it to generate
some potential tactics that
would be of interest.
And now you do
the, your model has
predicted a set of one of
the actions, or tactics,
in this case.
And then you parse
that tactic because it
will be in the form of text.
So now you parse it into
a structured format.
And then you just execute it
via the proof environment.
And this could be Lean
or Coq or Isabelle.
And then after you do
that, in the lucky case,
you already hit QED,
and this is all done.
But if you fail, if
this tactic is invalid,
or there are still some
open goals that you still
need to resolve, in that
case, you get some feedback,
and then you augment the prompt
and then backtrack if needed.
And then, we also have
this retrieval phase
over here, which seem to add to
the performance of the system.
And here, you are also able
to query a lemma database
and bring in some
relevant lemmas
and then add it
back to the prompt.
And this process just
continues over and over
and over again until you have
resolved the original theorem,
or alternatively,
you have timed out.
So here's the prompt of the
system in a little bit more
detail.
So here, as you see, there is
the serialized proof state.
And here, you have
what is the goal
that you still have to prove.
And what are the hypotheses
that are being made.
So over here, for example,
the hypothesis include--
these are the assumptions
you're making, right?
So this includes x being of
type NAT, natural numbers.
And then, also, x being even.
And then you have
the goal, which
is x square modulo
2 is equal to 0.
We also have this information
about the last step.
So the way to read this is
that from left to right,
you are looking at successive
queries to the LLM.
So the first column
over here, this
includes information about
what is the first query
that you are making.
So the first thing
that you have done.
So let's say that
you already have
made this decision that you
are going to have this intro h
tactic, right?
So that's what created
that hypothesis, x squared
modulo 2 equals 0.
So then this is the last step.
This is stored in a stack and
fed as part of the prompt.
Now then, at this point
there has been no error.
So then, you get this
response from this LLM
after you feed this information
that the next thing that you
should do is RWH.
And then, now, if you
try to execute it,
you might get an error message
because the rewrite tactic
failed.
And then this information,
this error feedback,
you send it back to
the LLM, and then
that's the next You say
that, try again LLM.
And then the LLM says
that, OK, let's try apply
nat.mul_mod_right.
Now the details of this
tactic doesn't matter,
it's something involving
modular multiplication.
But the point is
this is also wrong.
So then, again,
at the next step,
you get an error feedback--
error message.
And this is something you
stick back into the prompt.
And then you make a query again.
And now it says, oh, let's try
this rewrite with nat.mul_mod.
And, yay, this time it works.
So now you see that the
interaction result doesn't
have any error message in it.
It's a success.
And so, this is now
put into the stack.
And so the last step,
as you see, has changed.
It's now rw nat.mul_mod.
So now you're going to try
to generate the next step.
And then this time it-- the
LLM generates this rw h, right.
And so this is how this
process is going to continue.
In a nutshell, you may query
the LLM, get some error message,
and then stick it
back into the prompt,
and then continue, right?
And this process
would just go on.
OK.
So this evaluation was done
in 2024, actually late 2023.
So the world has
changed since then.
But at least at that point,
we compared with GPT-4
and found that GPT-4 frequently
gave incorrect errors,
incorrect proofs.
And by contrast, this feedback
with the proof environment,
Lean in this case,
really helped for COPRA.
And so, even though it was
using the same underlying model,
the interaction allowed it
to create a correct proof
in this case.
Here are some
experimental results.
You can see the
details in the paper.
But in this picture,
on the x-axis,
you see the number of queries.
And on the y-axis, you see
the number of theorems proved.
So what we saw over here is
that, pretty quickly, the COPRA
approach was able to
prove a lot of theorems
with a relatively small
number of queries.
Whereas the other approaches,
that didn't get that far.
And here is an evaluation
on miniF2F test.
So the absolute
numbers are not great.
But then the amount
of compute we
provided COPRA was
also relatively small.
We just allowed 60
queries per proof attempt.
Now what we saw here was
that we got quite reasonable
performance, comparable with
the state-of-the-art methods.
Now, of course,
since then, the state
of the art on this benchmark
has moved quite a bit.
So miniF2F, for those of you
who don't know, is, by the way,
it's a compilation of
computation mathematics
problems, mostly at
the high school level.
And so it's of the form
that here is a theorem
and come up with a lean proof.
So here, what we
see is that there
was this around 29% or
30% success rate, which
is behind the current SOTA.
But I think one
question would be that
if you take this approach
and scale it up, then
where would you end up?
And there are no public
results on that yet.
So in this talk,
though, I'm going
to go beyond the method
that we just presented,
which is the basic COPRA, and
talk about some results that we
just recently developed.
This is not published yet.
And here, we are leveraging
the ability of LLMs
to abstract and also to use
natural language reasoning,
because I think
that this is really
where the sort of approach
that we just presented.
This shines because of
the tremendous amount
of world knowledge that
is stored inside LLMs.
We can really use them in a
lot more powerful capacity
than just as a predictor
of the next tactic.
And so, here's a sample problem.
This is from IMO.
And this is saying that,
prove that this fraction is
irreducible for every
natural number n.
So what we'll see is
that the COPRA approach
can be extended a little
bit to, in fact, come up
with a hierarchical
solution to this problem.
And so, this will involve
breaking down the problem
into subproblems and then
solving hierarchically.
OK, so how do we do this?
Well, first what
we do is that we
ask the LLM to come up
with an informal solution
to this problem.
And so, I don't know if this
font is too small to read,
but basically what is going on
here is that this was fed to 03,
a reasoning model, and so, it
was able to come up with this
step-by-step plan.
So, for example, you
first define the GCD
and then subtract to simplify.
Then you apply the
Euclidean algorithm.
And then you conclude
something about the GCD.
And then you have
the final conclusion.
So then, we say
that, OK, so let's
take this informal decomposition
and put it in the context.
Now, let's say
that it's our goal
to prove this lemma
in Lean 4, right?
So this is the formal
statement of the same problem.
And we are just
saying that, don't
try to write the proof, OK?
So let's just write the subgoals
that are needed to prove this.
But we are doing
this conditioned
on the informal proof
that we just generated.
And so, here is the proof of--
or here is the
decomposition of this lemma.
So what you see is that it comes
up with these three subgoals.
So first, you show that
this GCD step 1 is true.
And it's basically saying that
this GCD of 21n plus 4 times 14n
plus 3 is the same
as the GCD of this.
14n plus 3 times 7n plus 1.
So then there is the second
one, and there's the third one,
and so on and so forth.
And then, finally, you
have the main theorem
that combines all of the above.
So the appeal of this
sort of decomposition
is that now this
very complex problem
has been simplified into
these three subproblems, which
are a lot more tractable.
So then in the
next step, we then
ask COPRA to solve the
subproblems one by one.
And what we see is
that COPRA is, in fact,
able to come up with these
proofs of the subproblems.
And here we are.
Here are the proofs.
Again, I'm not going to go
into the details of the proofs.
This is something that you have
to stare at for a little bit.
And it's not actually
especially complicated.
But then, once you have
proven these lemmas,
then you just put them
all in the context,
and then you also put
in the informal proof,
and then you ask Copra to
prove the full theorem.
And it is able to do that.
But COPRA is not
able to prove this
if you were giving it just this
entire theorem all as one block
and just asked it to solve.
So what we did here
is really something
that is a highly powerful
design pattern in LLM agents.
LLM agents are
extraordinarily flexible.
So with just some variations
on the ways you do prompting,
you are able to make it
do very, very different
things, things that would take
a tremendous amount of training
if you weren't using
these pre-trained models.
And so what we did
over here is that we
started with a
system that was just
designed to be a step-by-step
predictor of a low-level proof.
And then we made it do
high-level reasoning
at this more abstract
level, right,
because if you can
think of these subgoals
as basically being
abstractions of subproblems.
And so the LLM is able to
create these abstractions.
And once you have created--
made use of these abstractions,
your proof process
becomes a lot simpler,
because now you're
able to go hierarchically.
And all of this
was doable without
any substantial training.
You were just using
the power of prompting.
And to me, this is
a huge revelation,
the idea that you can use
the power of language,
the power of all of the
stored knowledge inside LLMs,
and then combine
that with this sort
of higher-level algorithmics
where you just put together
the informal and formal
reasoning steps in various ways
and change the
prompting strategy,
and you get something
that is qualitatively
different in capability.
And now it turns out that
the Lean feedback here
was also really important
because at least
with o3-mini, what we found is
that there were hallucinated
lemmas and so on.
And the grounding that was
provided by the Lean theorem
prover was absolutely critical
to solve this problem.
So now I want to
talk a little bit
about a different
application of the same idea.
This is in the context of formal
system verification, which
is one of the most
practical applications
of rigorous
mathematical reasoning.
And so, what you're doing
in formal verification
is that you are mathematically
modeling a real-world system
as a set of definitions,
and then you
are modeling system
properties as theorems
involving these definitions.
And then you're
proving these theorems.
These methods have led to
extremely rigorous systems,
systems that are
very difficult to--
or almost impossible to hack.
For example, there was this
time in a program organized
by the US Department
of Defense, they
used this formally verified
Linux kernel called seL4 to--
and they put this on a drone.
And then they got
a red team to try
to attack this drone for
a period of six weeks,
and they failed because
the rigor provided
by formal verification
was just so much.
Now, historically,
formal verification
has been extremely expensive,
and as a result, it's costs--
it's not really
been widely deployed
because the costs are not
justifiable except in the most
safety-critical scenarios.
However, with the rise of
AI, especially AI for math,
the cost-benefit equation
changes quite drastically.
And now, you can imagine
doing not only proofs of math,
but proofs of
real-world systems of,
for example, correctness,
security, performance, and so
on, using this growing
generation of AI tools.
So here, I'm going to show you
a basic example of this idea.
This can be scaled
up substantially
with more powerful
models and more compute.
But here, what we
are going to do
is to give you a very,
very basic compiler
and then show how to formally
verify its correctness.
Now this is so
simple, the compiler,
that it's almost a joke.
But trust me, when you go to
more advanced compiler design,
the fundamentals don't change.
It's really the
same sort of idea,
it's just that there
is more complexity.
Now, OK, to do
compiler verification,
you would need the
following pieces.
So first of all, you would need
to have a notion of a language.
And a language consists
of a syntax and semantics.
So syntax is a
grammar that defines
the form of the programs.
And then semantics are
the rules that define
the executions of programs.
And then a compiler
is basically a set
of rules that translate programs
from one language to another.
And then verifications
is that you
prove that the rules
preserve semantics.
So here, we are going to talk
about a very basic expression
language in which you are
allowed to do addition
and multiplication.
So this is just basic
arithmetic expressions.
And the syntax that
you see over here,
this is in a
language called Coq.
And here it looks
a lot like Lean.
It's similar, dependently typed,
functional programming language.
And so, what you're
doing over here
is that you're defining
this binary operator.
This can be either
plus or times.
You're defining this
notion of an expression.
And this is saying that it
can be either a constant
or a binary operation.
And then, there
are some rules that
tell you how to actually
evaluate these expressions.
If you're given an
expression, what
will be the result
when you evaluate it?
And I'm not going to go
into the rules in detail,
I'll share the slides.
And if you are
interested, you can--
well, you can look up
many resources on the web.
But also, I'm happy to answer
questions over email offline
or, actually, after this talk.
OK, so then you define
the source language.
So here, what you see is
that you can define the rules
that we saw previously.
They allow you to
define the semantics
of quite complex expression.
So here, what you're saying
is that you have a Const 2,
so an expression can be a
constant or a binary operation
or the result of a
binary operation.
And you see that
this is the result
of applying a binary
operation to two expressions.
And so, this is a recursive
definition, really.
And then you are getting
an expression as output.
So here what you are
saying is that you
can evaluate various complicated
expressions in this way.
And so, now you have to define
the target language, right?
So this is the--
a compiler is a mapping from
a source language to a target
language.
So now you have to define
the target language.
And so, what you
did over here is
that you are defining
the target language
as a list of instructions.
So a program is a
list of instructions.
And an instruction
is either this sort
of a constant expression or a
binary operation expression.
So one way to see it is that
while the original expression
in the source language was
defined in this recursive way,
in the target language, when
you are interpreting it,
you are doing it using a stack.
So this is a well-known idea
in programming languages
that if you have a
recursive expression,
let's say an
arithmetic expression,
then the way you can execute
it is by maintaining a stack.
And you can keep pushing
the current instruction
on the stack.
And you can basically do
this kind of a low-level--
build up a low-level
machine, a stack machine.
Actually, a lot
of early computers
were based on this idea.
And then the stack basically
keeps pushing new things on it.
And then you pop,
and then you read
the value that was just popped.
So, while very basic,
it still captures
a lot of important
programming language concepts.
Now, the point is
that I want to believe
that the mapping that I
would do between these two
representations is
actually correct.
But, of course, first I
have to define the compiler.
And so, this is the compiler.
So what this says
is that I am going
to take my input expression
in the source language.
And then I'm going to
do a pattern matching.
I'm going to consider these
two cases, either when
it's a constant or when
it's a binary operation.
And in each of these
cases, I'm going
to generate a target
language program.
So in the target
language program,
the entire sequence
of instructions
is just written down as a list.
Now, it's when you are
executing the program that you
are maintaining a stack, right?
That's when you are doing
all of the, kind of,
modeling the recursion.
But in the program itself, you
are just doing this kind of a--
you are generating the
instructions from E2.
You are generating the
instructions from E1,
and then you are
sticking this b.
And then you are just
building up a stack with--
or a sequence of instructions
with all of this.
So, for example, if you
started with this expression
Binop plus Const 2 Const 3.
So this is 2 plus 3 is,
that's really the expression.
And so then, in the
lower level language,
it's going to look like this.
So then, you have to define
this correctness theorem, which
says that for all e in the--
all expressions e in
the source language,
upon compiling this
expression, you
get something that,
when you execute it
in the programming
language's semantics,
you get the same thing
as if you evaluated
the original expression in the
source language's semantics.
So these two are the same.
Now, it turns out that COPRA
cannot prove this theorem just
in one shot.
So what you do instead
is that you ask the LLM.
Again, think of the IMO
example that I showed,
this is quite similar.
So you ask the LLM to invent
a lemma, an intermediate goal.
So the LLM goes ahead
and thinks for a while.
And this is o1 here.
And it comes up with
this intermediate lemma,
which basically says
that, rather than trying
to prove the entire compiler
correct, what you instead do
is that you just show
one step of compilation,
like for one subexpression,
that's going to be correct.
So basically, that's
the target theorem.
The auxiliary lemma is saying
that you can compile one
instruction correctly first.
And so this is really just
simplifying the problem,
breaking it down in
a step-by-step way.
And then we ask COPRA to come
up with a proof of this one
instruction.
And it's able to,
which is fantastic.
But then, what we
can do is, just
in the way we did previously,
we stick this back.
We take this proof, give
it to the COPRA agent,
put it in the
prompt, and then ask
it to prove the entire
theorem correct.
And it's now able to do this.
So, that's what I have
on this particular topic.
In summary, I would say that
mathematical discovery with LLM
agents is extremely promising.
I think that you can go a
very long distance with just
in-context learning.
But you want to have
the proof assistant
feedback for proper grounding.
And there is a lot of
higher-level agent design
that you can do where you
can combine agents that
are doing, for example,
formalization with agents that
are doing hierarchical
planning with agents
that are doing low-level stuff,
low-level proof generation.
And this is a very new space.
There is a lot to
be done over here.
Now, one question,
again, going back
to something we
asked previously.
Can you get rid of
this interaction
by just pushing the
whole thing to training?
Maybe you generate a lot of
training data in this way
by interaction with
the prover, and then
you just continue training
the LLM with those tracers.
And then at some point, the
LLM just gets good enough.
We are not there yet.
But maybe this is a world
that we can get to someday.
But currently, we have
to have these sorts
of agent architectures.
Now there's this paper
several of us recently wrote.
And you may have seen a
reference to this paper
previously.
Kaiyu is the lead
author of this,
and Dawn was the leader
of the overall effort.
But if you are curious
about this area,
you want to know more about
specific challenges, roadmaps,
then I would recommend that
you go and look at this paper.
I had a few things to say
about open challenges,
but I'm going to skip those
in the interest of time.
And I'm going to move on
to the next topic, which
is AI for scientific discovery,
because I want to emphasize
that this idea of LLM agents,
this has a lot of value
in this sort of
deductive mathematics,
where you are starting
with a set of principles,
a set of axioms,
definitions, and then you
are proving statements
in a step-by-step way.
But it also has
tremendous potential
in empirical discovery,
which is what happens
in most of the natural sciences,
where you are starting with data
and then you are trying
to fit some hypotheses
or some experimental claim, yes,
or some claims to this data.
Now, we'll see that this is also
a place where the abstraction
abilities of LLMs play
a potentially very
interesting role.
OK.
So very quickly, this is
what a natural science
process looks like.
You choose a research question.
You generate some hypotheses.
You do an experimental
setup, you collect some data,
you do some analysis of the
data, you interpret the data.
And then you report
to the community.
And so, just as an
example of this,
if you think of the world of
astronomy, back in the day,
there was this problem
that was observed,
which is that people
believed that the Earth was
the center of the solar system.
But then some of the planets
appeared to move backward,
and so this led to this
creation of this new hypothesis
that, in fact, we have
a heliocentric model.
And then this led
to the creation--
the collection of more data.
Tycho Brahe, in particular,
observed Mars and then came up
with a whole bunch of precise
measurements of the planet's
positions.
And then, Kepler chose
to analyze this data
and then fit a wide variety of
geometric shapes to this data.
And then he came up with
this, Kepler's third law.
And then, this eventually led
to Newton's law of gravitation.
So there was this
process that happened
in science, which involved
trading in abstractions.
Seeing some data
and then coming up
with this law in terms
of abstract principles,
but then further generalizing
it into a law that
was even more explanatory.
So I think that LLM agents
have tremendous potential
in automating a lot of
pieces of this pipeline.
And in particular
here, we are going
to focus on the problem of
symbolic regression, which
is the task of coming
up with equations based
on empirical observations.
So, for example,
an instance of that
would be that if you were given
these measurements of planet
Mars and then you wanted
to discover Kepler's law,
how do you do that
from the data?
Now, one would think
that LLMs would not
be a great fit for this problem
because the data is just
really low level, right?
This is just a bunch of numbers.
However, it turns out that LLMs
do have a tremendous potential
over here in the
sense that they can
bring in prior scientific
knowledge into the picture.
What you have to do,
though, is that you
have to complement
the use of LLMs
with the use of other machinery
that is able to, for example,
evaluate hypotheses on the data
and give you some notion of how
well it performed.
So once you have that kind
of a mechanism for evaluating
LLM-generated hypotheses, you
can create an agentic loop
where you have more and more
feedback going to the LLM.
And then this process
of hypothesis generation
is left to the LLM.
Whereas hypothesis evaluation
is done by some other entity.
And if you think of it,
it's not fundamentally
different from the
way we use Lean
or the proof assistant in the
previous part of the lecture.
So one of the most
established approaches
to symbolic regression
is genetic programming.
And here are some visualizations
from a system called PySR, which
is quite popular in this space.
And so, what's going
on here is that you
have a pool of candidate
expressions, candidate
equations being maintained.
And then you have mutation
and crossover operations
being applied to those.
And then, you are generating--
you're updating this pool of
expressions using feedback
from a separate machinery that
is evaluating these expressions
and telling you, how
good is the loss?
How well does this
match the reality
that is there in the data?
So this has had a lot of impact.
There are applications in
physics and other areas as well.
And so, here are
some example papers.
So one thing that's
interesting is that if you just
imagine how does this process
of genetic programming go on.
So there is this
pool of expressions
that is being evolved.
And so, what you see
is that there are
these islands of expressions.
So these clusters which contain
expressions that are of--
that have something in
common between them.
So one way to think about
how LLMs are relevant
is that these clusters or
islands of expressions, these
capture various kinds of--
various classes of functions.
So, for example, in
this red one over here,
you may have
exponential functions.
In this case, you may have
trigonometric functions
where you have the cosines.
And so one way to
imagine this is
that an LLM looking at these
expressions, because LLMs
are good at coding
and associating code
with natural language,
could perhaps
come up with some
explanation of what
this piece of code, this
expression, is actually doing.
And that's the
idea of abstraction
that we are going to use.
So this paper was
at NeurIPS last year
and co-led by Aria
Grayeli, who was
an undergrad at UT, and
Atharva Sehgal, who's
a PhD student at UT.
And so, the starting
point here is
that we want to do this
kind of concept abstraction.
And so, what we want
to be able to do
is that we want to look at these
variety of laws, which come
from very different contexts.
But then we should be
able to look at this
and kind of tell that
what's going on here
is that you have this power
law thing going on, right?
And so, the other
thing we want to do
is that we want to use
background knowledge that
was created by a physicist or
that's there inside an LLM.
So, for example,
here, you have an LLM,
a concept that
has been produced,
which is that wave
strain diminishes
as distance increases.
This is, let's say, a
property of black holes.
And so, you want to
be able to associate
this kind of
information, this is
a piece of common sense,
knowledge to equations.
So this equation, for example,
satisfies these properties.
But this is-- you want to create
a mapping between these two
things.
And because, if you imagine
how the scientific process is
ongoing, so let's say you
have an AI that is predicting
equations based
on data, you also
want it to be
conditioned on this sort
of high-level knowledge that is
being given by a human expert,
right?
And so, you want to have this
association between code,
that is these
equations and language.
So the way we set up this
symbolic regression problem
using LLMs is something like
this, that we imagine that--
and actually, here,
it's not just LLMs.
It's more like a
combination of LLMs
and this sort of abstraction
into high-level concepts.
And so, we imagine that
there is this universe
of high-level concepts.
So, for example, wave
strain diminishes
as distance increases or power
laws or sinusoidal functions.
These are sort of high-level
ideas that we have in our head.
And there is a notion of a data
set, which is the concrete data
that you want to fit.
And then you have a space
of programmatic hypotheses.
This is, for example, the
landscape of equation--
or the set of equations
expressible in Python
or in some restricted
DSL inside Python.
And then, what you're
saying is that you
want to jointly
infer, given the data,
this distribution over
pi, which is likely
hypothesis and likely concepts.
So you don't want to just
get likely programs, given
the data, which
would be the goal
of traditional
symbolic regression.
You want to get both
the programs and also
the kinds of concepts
that they represent.
Because ultimately, you want
to explain these programs
to a human scientist.
Or alternatively, maybe
this joint distribution
gives you more information
than if you just
operated in the program space.
And so, this you can
factorize in this way.
And then it turns out that
the way to think about it
is that p of D given
pi, is basically
saying that if I have a
particular program pi, what
is the likelihood of the data?
So how well does the
program explain the data.
In order to find this, you just
execute the program, right?
And see what kinds
of results come out.
And what the likelihood
of the data set is.
And p of pi given C is
basically telling you
that, OK, here are these--
here is the concept that I have.
So let's say I'm thinking
about power laws, OK?
So conditioned on
this concept that I'm
thinking about power laws,
what is the probability
of this program that this
piece of code, right?
To what extent does this piece
of code represent a power law?
And this is something that an
LLM has background knowledge
inside it to do.
And then, finally,
I have this p of C,
which is a prior over concepts.
And this is also
something that an LLM
knows that I have seen the
literature of, let's say,
physics until this point.
So what is the likelihood
of this concept?
So all of this together
gives you, ultimately,
the ability to infer both a
distribution over both programs
and concepts.
Now, in order to
really implement this--
this is the loop
that we came up with.
So this follows
the basic structure
of an evolutionary algorithm.
But it does this sort of
Bayesian concept learning thing
guided by LLMs on top of that.
And so, operationally,
the way to think about it
is that you have, like in
any evolutionary algorithm,
you're maintaining a population
of hypotheses or programs.
And then, at this
point, you have a choice
of doing evolution,
either guided
by the classical
symbolic method where
you're doing some random
tweaks to the abstract syntax
tree of the program.
Or alternatively, you are doing
this LLM-guided evolution, where
you are saying that
here is a concept,
here is a program
that I have, and I
want to generate a new program.
And when you are
doing that, you are
being guided by this concept
library, which tells you
that, these are the
concepts that I'm
thinking about right now.
So power laws seem really
good, really well-suited
to this condition-- this
concept or this setting.
Or maybe trigonometric
functions seem
especially well-suited to
this setting, and so on.
So you are feeding all of that
to this LLM-guided evolution
process, and that allows
you to basically mutate
the current programs
into new programs.
And then, after you
do that, you are, like
in the usual
evolutionary way, you
are identifying the best
candidates in this population.
And so, this is where you use
the fitness function, which
is how well does your hypothesis
pool explain the data that you
have?
And this is where that p of
D given pi that comes in.
And so, this is a
little bit more detail
about how the hypothesis
evolution works.
So you start with this
initialization, initial program
population, and then
you're evaluating.
You're getting the best program.
You're mutating
or crossing over.
And then you're replacing
the oldest program.
And then this process just
carries on for a while.
So the important
thing over here is
that you are using the LLM
for implementing this mutation
and crossover operations.
So, in particular,
rather than in
a classical genetic algorithm,
what's going to happen
is that you're given
the AST and you're
going to say that, OK,
swap out this subtree
by a different subtree.
Now you're going to say that I'm
going to ask the LLM to rewrite
the program into something.
And this idea was also
used in the FunSearch paper
from DeepMind last year.
And FunSearch has
been very successful.
The way in which this LaSR
work differs from FunSearch
is fundamentally in its use
of this concept library.
But a lot of the other
ideas are closely related.
So this is just to
highlight the difference
between the symbolic crossover
versus the LLM crossover.
So in this case, the LLM is
basically doing all this.
It's being given
a crossover prompt
and then it's given some
formatting instructions,
and then it's generating
the new expression.
So after you do this,
there is the-- so
you have evolved
your hypothesis.
So now you have this new pool.
And now you also evolve
your concept library.
And so the concept library,
this evolution process
has these two stages.
So first, you take
your new programs
that you have created,
your new program pool,
and now you're asking
the LLM to abstract this
into these natural language
high-level descriptions.
So, for example, here,
the LLM is telling you
that, Oh, this equation
represents exponential growth
or decay.
And then, the LLM--
the concept evolution
process is just
like the hypothesis or
program evolution process,
except it now uses this--
an LLM to basically combine,
mash up these different concepts
into a new concept.
So, for example, here, you see
that exponential growth decay,
this is one concept.
Another concept says
depends on temperature.
And our LLM, because it
has all this knowledge
about all sorts of concepts
relevant in physics,
it comes up with
this idea that, oh,
this should be a
Boltzmann distribution.
This is a useful
concept to have.
And then this is
going to influence
the hypothesis evolution, which
is going to influence concept
abstraction and evolution.
And this loop will continue.
So one way to visualize this is
that after the first phase, when
you have done this
hypothesis evolution,
you may have these islands of
different kinds of expressions.
Now, in the concept generation
process, concept discovery
process, you're going to
get these natural language
descriptions of these
different islands.
So this is sinusoidal trends,
this is power law trends,
this is linear trends, this is
exponential trends, and so on.
And then, what we
found is that the use
of this sort of a
high-level concept library
helped us in this equation
discovery process.
So we evaluated this on this
task of equation discovery--
or discovering Feynman
equations, just given
the prompt that--
so there was the
data, but then there
was a prompt that told
you which chapter you
were looking at, and so on.
And so what we found
is that this approach
proved more effective than a
version where you were just
using, either pure
genetic programming or one
where you were not using any
kind of concept learning.
And so it turns out that even
with local language models, when
we didn't use a
frontier model, we
were still able to outperform
this genetic programming
approach.
And the overall
finding was that--
and you can find more
details in the paper--
is that the use of this
sort of high-level concepts
generated by the LLM, it
accelerates discovery.
Now, one appeal of this
sort of LLM-based approach
is that it can very naturally
take in user-provided hints.
So, in this case, we
gave the algorithm
some hints, which was this
is the kind of equation you
are looking at.
So in the previous experiments
actually, we did not have hints.
So this was just
purely based on data.
But then, in this
case, we had hints,
and then we found that hints
actually provided some benefits.
So on the x-axis here, you
have the number of iterations.
On the y-axis, you have the
fraction of equations solved.
And then we found that
the use of the hints, It
provided a modest benefit at
least earlier on in the process.
So here is an example
of this in action.
So here, this is the
classic Coulomb's law.
And then PySR is this
genetic programming approach,
and it gave this very unwieldy
kind of expression that,
it turns out, is equivalent
to the ground truth expression
but it required a lot of
simplification for you to-- it
would require a lot
of simplification
for you to go from here
to the ground truth.
Whereas the LaSR approach
is able to basically--
because of some of the knowledge
that is there in the LLM,
it's able to reduce to
ground truth after four
steps of simplification.
Now you could say, wait a
second, isn't the LLM cheating?
Because it already has
Coulomb's law in its mind.
So how do you know that
this is not just leakage?
And, of course, in this case,
there is that possibility.
But that said, I would say
that the attraction here
is that the input to the system
is just this data, right?
It's just the
input-output values for--
that would result
from Coulomb's law.
And it's a very
low-level kind of input.
The fact that it was able
to fit this to Coulomb's law
is kind of interesting.
But that said, we also did other
experiments on synthetic data
where you just manufactured
a completely weird equation
and a weird data set
coming from that equation,
and then ask the system
to regenerate this.
And we found that there were
substantial benefits even
in that case.
So here is some information
about some of the concepts
that you ended up
getting from LaSR.
So you see there is stuff like,
good mathematical expressions,
exhibit symmetry or regularity.
But that said, there were
also some expressions
that were really--
that didn't really
seem to mean anything.
But at the same time,
there is no guarantee
about the quality
of the concepts.
This is all natural
language at this point.
An interesting
possibility is to use
some kind of a formal
language to describe
the high-level concepts.
Now we also use this in
a new discovery problem,
because we were also worried
about the possibility of this
being an artifact of leakage
in case of standard benchmarks
like discovering
Feynman equations.
And so, we used this method
to come up with a new scaling
law for LLMs.
And so, here, what you see is
the so-called chinchilla law.
So this is a law that was
postulated in a DeepMind paper
from a few years back.
And so here, basically
what you're trying to do
is to predict the
loss of the LLM
based on these various
hyperparameters.
And so, this was the law.
So you postulate a scaling
law, you measure model loss
with respect to
hyperparameters, and then you
fit scaling law to data set.
And in order to do
this, of course,
you would need to
have a data set
where you have a lot of values
of these hyperparameters
and corresponding accuracy
values for the LLM.
Now, we did the same
thing with LaSR.
Rather than fitting
a hand-fitted law,
which was done in
the Chinchilla paper.
So they basically
postulated a law like this,
and then they fit
the parameters.
But by contrast, what
we did is that we just
asked LaSR to go find it.
And LaSR was able to come up
with this sort of a law, where
we also had this parameter
called number of shots, which
is that, if you are
doing prediction,
what is the number of
examples that you're
giving it in context.
And this parameter is available
in some of these data sets.
And so what we found is that
there was this interesting kind
of law that came up.
Now, this is just one example.
It's not really very
comprehensive yet,
but this just shows
that you can make
these kinds of new
discoveries using this law.
And so, basically, if
you interpret this,
the way to think about it is
that a large number of shots
gives poor results for
low capability models,
but then, once the models pass
a capability threshold, then
having more shots helps, right?
And this is sort of a common
sense linguistic interpretation
of the law that came out.
So you can also do
something after this.
So if you're thinking about--
thinking of yourself as
an LLM scaling law person,
you start with the Chinchilla
law from the previous paper,
and then you say,
OK, maybe I should
bring in this insight about
shots into the Chinchilla law.
Combine the old chinchilla law
with this new discovery that
was made by LaSR, and then
you find that this modified
chinchilla actually
is able to do
better than both the old
chinchilla and also the LaSR
itself.
And so, this is kind
of interesting that--
and shows that this discovery
process using LLM agents--
and this is very
much an agent, right?
This is not just a one-shot LLM.
You're using an LLM combined
with this various other tools.
And so, what you are
getting out of this is
can influence human
discovery as well
and lead to something
that is greater
than the sum of the parts.
So in the interest of time, I'm
going to skip this next bit.
But what I said there is
that these ideas can also
be applied to settings
where you have
visual high-dimensional
inputs, because now we have
visual language models as well.
So you can go crazy
and build these kinds
of evolution-based agents,
where you have VLMS
as part of the story.
And I'm extremely optimistic
about this direction.
So, in summary, I would say
that LLM-directed evolution
is a powerful tool
for empirical science.
And this point has already been
made previously by FunSearch,
but now we see that we
can make it even more
powerful with these
ideas of abstraction
that LLMs can give you
basically for free.
And even this can
be even extended
to visual settings where you
have to use now visual language
models.
But hey, they're coming a long
way-- they have come a long way.
And importantly, the
abstraction abilities of LLMs
can also be really helpful here.
Open challenges, verification
of hypothesis and concepts,
concept representations that
go beyond natural language,
scaling to larger search
spaces, input dimensions,
and then even going beyond
hypothesis generation
to other parts of the
scientific discovery process.
But at the end, though,
I am very optimistic that
LLM agents, not just LLMs, but
these kinds of agentic workflows
where you have
combinations of LLM queries
as well as other
kinds of machinery,
they can be extremely powerful
in scientific discovery.
They can help you come up with
new scientific hypotheses,
and even do experiment design.
And also, as we saw, in
mathematical discovery,
they can be supremely powerful.
And again, we are just
in the early stages
of what I think this
research-- line of research
will end up being.
And this can have applications
in math, in science,
in engineering, as you saw the
formal verification application,
building rigorous systems.
So the future is very bright.
And with that, I'll end.
I want to thank all my
collaborators and funders.
And I'm happy to take questions.